<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="jats2html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
	<journal-meta>
		<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CISS</journal-id>
		<journal-title-group>
			<journal-title>CISS - Current Issues in Sport Science</journal-title>
			<abbrev-journal-title>CISS</abbrev-journal-title>
		</journal-title-group>
		<issn pub-type="epub">2414-6641</issn>
		<publisher>
			<publisher-name>Bern Open Publishing</publisher-name>
			<publisher-loc>Berne, Switzerland</publisher-loc>
		</publisher>
	</journal-meta>
	<article-meta>
		<article-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.36950/2022ciss007</article-id>
		<title-group>
			<article-title>Further thoughts on promoting sustainable behavior change in physical activity settings – comment on Hohberg et al.</article-title>
		</title-group>
		<contrib-group>
			<contrib contrib-type="author">
				<name>
					<surname>Ntoumanis</surname>
					<given-names>Nikos</given-names>
				</name>
				<email>nntoumanis@health.sdu.dk</email>
				<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref>
				<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">author_email</xref>
			</contrib>
		<aff id="aff1">
			<label>a</label>Danish Centre for Motivation and Behaviour Science, IOB, <institution>University of Southern Denmark</institution>, Odense, <country>Denmark</country> &amp; 
			School of Health and Welfare, <institution>Halmstad University</institution>, Halmstad, <country>Sweden</country>
		</aff>
		</contrib-group>
		<author-notes>
		<corresp id="cor1">
			<label>author_email</label>Corresponding author e-mail: <email>nntoumanis@health.sdu.dk</email>
		</corresp>
		</author-notes>
		<pub-date pub-type="epub">
			<day>22</day>
			<month>11</month>
			<year>2022</year>
		</pub-date>
		<volume>7</volume>
		<history>
			<date date-type="received">
				<day>18</day>
				<month>10</month>
				<year>2022</year>
			</date>
			<date date-type="accepted">
				<day>18</day>
				<month>10</month>
				<year>2022</year>
			</date>
		</history>
		<permissions>
			<copyright-statement>Copyright © 2022, N. Ntoumanis. This work is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International.</copyright-statement>
			<copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
			<copyright-holder>N. Ntoumanis</copyright-holder>
			<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
				<license-p>This work is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International.</license-p>
			</license>
		</permissions>
		<abstract>
		<p><bold>Abstract</bold></p>
		<p>In this commentary, I provide some reflections on the target article’s discussion of the role of affect for physical activity 
		promotion. I also offer further thoughts and suggestions on how to promote sustainable behavior change, addressing both conceptual and 
		methodological issues.</p>
		</abstract>
		<kwd-group>
			<kwd>affect</kwd>
			<kwd>physical activity</kwd>
			<kwd>flexible habits</kwd>
			<kwd>MOST design</kwd>
			<kwd>multi-component intervention</kwd>
			<kwd>sustainable</kwd>
		</kwd-group>
	</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
	<sec id="introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<p>The Target Article by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">Hohberg et al., (2022)</xref> provides a number of interesting perspectives on how physical activity (PA) interventions 
	should be conceptualized, implemented, and evaluated. The Move for Life intervention, highlighted in that article, is indeed a good 
	example of how a whole systems approach can result not just in effective research projects, but also in community programs that are 
	acceptable and can be implemented at scale. The authors of the Target Article make a number of interesting suggestions for future research 
	for the field of physical activity promotion. These approaches cover a number of important conceptual and methodological issues.</p>
	<sec id="further-thoughts">
		<title>Further Thoughts</title>
		<p>One of the authors’ recommendations is to pay more attention to affective mechanisms and dual process models. It is without doubt 
		important that exercise and leisure time PA should be associated with pleasant (or at least not unpleasant!) affective experiences. 
		Whilst the authors are correct in that some cognitive approaches are still frequently utilized in the PA promotion literature, such 
		approaches have been heavily criticized (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">Sniehotta et al., 2014</xref>). In fact, other salient conceptual frameworks with a heavy 
		cognitive component do acknowledge the role of positive affective experiences. For instance, self-determination theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">Ryan &amp; 
		Deci, 2017</xref>) identifies intrinsic motivation, engaging in an activity because of the inherent pleasure and fun the activity provides, as 
		the most adaptative form of motivation. Furthermore, interventions using this theory highlight, amongst other things, the important 
		role of affective experiences when communicating about behavior change (e.g., acknowledging negative feelings, emphatic listening; 
		<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">Teixeira et al., 2020</xref>). Other integrative frameworks of behavioral regulation developed for PA, such as the Action Control Framework 
		(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">Rhodes &amp; Gray, 2018</xref>) integrate affective processes (e.g., reflective affect, manipulated affect through volitional regulation, 
		and reflexive affect) with cognitive mechanisms (e.g., intention formation). In short, the criticism that affective mechanisms are 
		neglected in contemporary literature on the psychology of PA is potentially overstated. Where the problem might lie is that many 
		interventions do not give affect the attention it deserves. The authors of the Target Article offer some good suggestions for 
		supervised interventions that could prevent negative automatic affective valuations. These suggestions could be augmented by other 
		examples that harness digital solutions and have the potential for upscaling. As an example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">Conroy and Kim (2021)</xref> successfully tested 
		a mobile application for conditioning associations between physical activity and pleasure.</p>
		<p>Other potential fruitful avenues for future research on PA promotion might focus on promoting flexible habits. I use this term 
		differently from how the authors use it. I mean habits that are built not on strict routines (e.g., going for a walk on the same 
		time, in the same place, and following the same cue to walk), but flexible routines that allow variations in behavioral execution, and 
		hence are less susceptible to unexpected obstacles. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">Beshears et al. (2021)</xref> showed that paying exercisers to exercise 
		without a time constraint within any given day, led to more gym visits than paying exercises to exercise only within a two-hour 
		window; this difference was evident even when the incentives were removed. We know from the habits literature that building strong 
		habits promotes sustained behavior, including PA, but sometimes strict habits can become too inflexible and highly routinized, hence 
		undermining the affective experience of exercise. For instance, variety has been proposed as an important ingredient of exercise 
		motivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">Sylvester et al., 2018</xref>). Striking the right balance between consistency and flexibility in habit formation could be a 
		key research priority for future research on the psychology of PA promotion. Habit is just one of many behavior change techniques. The 
		recently proposed compendium of self-enactable techniques to change and self-manage motivation and behavior proposes over a hundred of 
		such techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">Knittle et al., 2021</xref>). Whilst not dismissing the role of the wider environment (e.g., social, physical, cultural) on 
		individual behavior, changing such environments takes time and concerted effort. The compendium proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">Knittle et al. (2021)</xref> could be 
		a useful resource to assist people in identifying what they can do on their own to manage their motivation and behavior, including 
		PA.</p>
		<p>Lastly, and very briefly, in terms of methodological advances, besides the suggestion given by the authors of the Target Article 
		for intensive longitudinal designs (which are useful for theory development and refinement), we should consider new ways of 
		developing and implementing field interventions. One such promising framework from the field of behavioral science is the Multiphase 
		Optimization Strategy (MOST; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">Collins, 2018</xref>). MOST designs can help PA researchers to fine-tune intervention components (e.g., through 
		factorial experiments) so that only components that are most efficacious, cost-effective, and parsimonious (or whatever the trial 
		optimization criteria are), are filtered through and subsequently used in randomized controlled trials. Currently, most of our PA 
		interventions are multi-component and these components have been compiled based on personal preference, convenience, and/or past 
		evidence, without being subjected to a rigorous selection procedure.</p>
		</sec>
	</sec>
</body>
<back>
	<ack>
		<sec sec-type="funding-statement">
			<p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors have no funding or support to report.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="COI-statement">
			<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="data-availability">
			<p><bold>Data availability statement:</bold> All relevant data are within the paper.</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="editors">
			<p><bold>Editorial team</bold></p>
			<p><bold>Editor-in-Chief:</bold> Claudio R. Nigg, University of Bern, Switzerland</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="cite-as">
			<p><bold>Cite as:</bold> Ntoumanis, N. (2022). Further thoughts on promoting sustainable behavior change in physical activity settings – comment on Hohberg et al. <italic>Current Issues in Sport Science (CISS), 7</italic>, Article 007. <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.36950/2022ciss007">https://doi.org/10.36950/2022ciss007</ext-link></p>
		</sec>
	</ack>
	<ref-list>
	<title>References</title>
		<ref id="r1"><mixed-citation>Beshears, J., Lee, H. N., Milkman, K. L., Mislavsky, R., &amp; Wisdom, J. (2021). Creating exercise habits using incentives: the 
		tradeoff between flexibility and routinization. <italic>Management Science, 67</italic>(7), 3985-4642. 
		<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1287/mnsc.2020.3706">https://doi.org/10.1287/mnsc.2020.3706</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r2"><mixed-citation>Collins, L., (2018). <italic>Optimization of behavioral, biobehavioral, and biomedical interventions: The Multiphase 
		Optimization Strategy (MOST)</italic>. Springer.</mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r3"><mixed-citation>Conroy, D. E., &amp; Kim, I. (2021). Heartphone: Mobile evaluative conditioning to enhance affective processes and promote physical 
		activity. <italic>Health Psychology, 40</italic>(12), 988-997. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/hea0000886">https://doi.org/10.1037/hea0000886</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r4"><mixed-citation>Hohberg, V., Kreppke, J.-N., Cody, R., Guthold, R., Woods, C., Brand, R., Dunton, G. F., Rothmann, A. J., Ketelhut, S., &amp; Nigg, 
		C. R. (2022). What is needed to promote physical activity? Current trends and new perspectives in theory, intervention, and 
		implementation. <italic>Current Issues in Sport Science (CISS), 7</italic>, Article 005. 
		<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.36950/2022ciss005">https://doi.org/10.36950/2022ciss005</ext-link>?</mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r5"><mixed-citation>Knittle, K., Heino, M., Marques, M. M., Stenius, M., Beattie, M., Ehbrecht, F., Hagger, M. S., Hardeman, W., &amp; Hankonen, N. (2020). 
		The compendium of self-enactable techniques to change and self-manage motivation and behaviour v.1.0. <italic>Nature Human Behaviour, 
		4</italic>(2), 215–223. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0798-9">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0798-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r6"><mixed-citation>Rhodes, R. E, &amp; Gray, S. M. (2018). Affect in the process of action control of health-protective behaviors. In D.M. Williams, R. E. 
		Rhodes &amp; M. T. Conner (Eds.), <italic>Affective Determinants of Health Behavior</italic> (pp. 21-47). Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r7"><mixed-citation>Ryan, R. M., &amp; Deci, E. L. (2017). <italic>Self-determination theory: Basic psychological needs in motivation, development and 
		wellness</italic>. Guilford Press.</mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r8"><mixed-citation>Sniehotta, F. F., Presseau, J., &amp; Araújo-Soares, V. (2014). Time to retire the theory of planned behaviour. <italic>Health 
		Psychology Review, 8</italic>(1), 1-7. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/17437199.2013.869710">https://doi.org/10.1080/17437199.2013.869710</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r9"><mixed-citation>Sylvester, B. D., Curran, T., Standage, M., Sabiston, C. M., &amp; Beauchamp, M. R. (2018). Predicting exercise motivation and exercise 
		behavior: A moderated mediation model testing the interaction between perceived exercise variety and basic psychological needs satisfaction. 
		<italic>Psychology of Sport and Exercise, 36</italic>, 50-56. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychsport.2018.01.004">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychsport.2018.01.004</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
		<ref id="r10"><mixed-citation>Teixeira, P. J., Marques, M. M., Silva, M. N., Brunet, J., Duda, J. L., Haerens, L., La Guardia, J., Lindwall, M., Lonsdale, C., Markland, 
		D., Michie, S., Moller, A. C., Ntoumanis, N., Patrick, H., Reeve, J., Ryan, R. M., Sebire, S. J., Standage, M., Vansteenkiste, M., … Hagger, 
		M. S. (2020). A classification of motivation and behavior change techniques used in self-determination theory-based interventions in 
		health contexts. <italic>Motivation Science, 6</italic>(4), 438-455. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/mot0000172">https://doi.org/10.1037/mot0000172</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
	</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
